Inventory of the Institute for Humane Studies Miscellaneous Records
Hoover Institution Archives
- Sound recordings of lectures, interviews, discussions, and meetings, 1955-1977; 141 sound tape reels (Box 1-10)
  - John Jewkes sound recordings, 1959 June
    - Lecture on John Kenneth Galbraith and the book The Affluent Society, 1959 June 25 (Box 6)
      Jewkes provides his thoughts on John Kenneth Galbraith and the book The Affluent Society. He argues that the book is appealing to people because it assures people they can be both humane and wealthy, where the contemporary, conventional wisdom holds the two as mutually exclusive. Jewkes finds Galbraith's history atrocious before examining Galbraith's economic arguments.
  - Bruno Leoni sound recordings
    - Which Freedom?, 1958 June 16 (Box 6)
      Use copy available. Hoover Identifier 85023_a_0008220
      Leoni examines the various definitions of the word "freedom." He argues the semantic differences between ideologies and/or locations is a serious problem. He calls for economists and politicians to work toward ending this problem, though he notes (with a nod to Ludwig von Mises) some people often purposefully misuse words for their own benefit.
      The text of the lecture was available from the Online Library of Liberty, http://oll.libertyfund.org/?option=com_staticxt&staticfile=show.php%3Ftitle=920&chapter=193186&layout=html&Itemid=27 as of 27 Aug 2012.
    - Freedom and Constraint, 1958 June 17 (Box 6)
      Use copy available. Hoover Identifier 85023_a_0008221
      The sound quality is terrible at the beginning and the end.
      In this talk, Leoni looks at how the concept of constraint defines what freedom is. As with his lecture the previous day, he touches on semantics, but for the most part looks at the contrast between freedom and constraint and how this defines both. He argues that freedom and liberty are the same thing and that it is ridiculous to argue about a freedom from some other thing.
      The text of the lecture was available from the Online Library of Liberty, http://oll.libertyfund.org/?option=com_staticxt&staticfile=show.php%3Ftitle=920&chapter=193188&layout=html&Itemid=27 as of 27 Aug 2012.
    - Freedom and the Rule of Law, 1958 June 18 (Box 6)
      Use copy available. Hoover Identifier 85023_a_0008224
      Leoni examines the rule of law, how it is fundamentally an English-speaking world creation, and its application around the world.
      The text of the lecture was available from The Online Library of Liberty, http://oll.libertyfund.org/?option=com_staticxt&staticfile=show.php%3Ftitle=920&chapter=193190&layout=html&Itemid=27 as of 27 Aug 2012.
    - Freedom and Certainty of the Law, 1958 June 19 (Box 6)
      Use copy available. Hoover Identifier 85023_a_0008225
      The sound quality is terrible at the head of the program.
      The text of the lecture was available from the Online Library of Liberty, http://oll.libertyfund.org/?option=com_staticxt&staticfile=show.php%3Ftitle=920&chapter=193192&layout=html&Itemid=27 as of 27 Aug 2012.
    - Freedom and Legislation, 1958 June 20 (Box 6)
      Use copy available. Hoover Identifier 85023_a_0008229
      The sound quality at the head of program is terrible.
      The text of the lecture was available from the Online Library of Liberty, http://oll.libertyfund.org/?option=com_staticxt&staticfile=show.php%3Ftitle=920&chapter=193194&layout=html&Itemid=27 as of 27 Aug 2012.
    - A group discussion with Bruno Leoni, 1958 June 20 (Box 7)
      Use copy available. Hoover Identifier 85023_a_0008234
      Concerns coercion, progressive taxation, etc.
    - Freedom and Representation, 1958 June 23 (Box 7)
      Use copy available. Hoover Identifier 85023_a_0008237
      Includes a discussion at the end about market and political aspects of stockholder voting and rights in the modern corporation.
      The text of the lecture was available from the Online Library of Liberty, http://oll.libertyfund.org/?option=com_staticxt&staticfile=show.php%3Ftitle=920&chapter=193196&layout=html&Itemid=27 as of 27 Aug 2012.
    - Freedom and Commonwealth, 1958 June 25 (Box 7)
      Use copy available. Hoover Identifier 85023_a_0008238
      This lecture is about group decisions and individual choices.
      The sound quality is suboptimal at times, with a high-pitched squeal audible.
      The text of the lecture was available from the Online Library of Liberty, http://oll.libertyfund.org/?option=com_staticxt&staticfile=show.php%3Ftitle=920&chapter=193198&layout=html&Itemid=27 as of JS, 27 Aug 2012.
    - Possibility of a Restoration of a Maximum Area of Free Individual Choice, 1958 June 27 (Box 7)
      Use copy available. Hoover Identifier 85023_a_0008242
      The text of the lecture was available from the Online Library of Liberty, http://oll.libertyfund.org/?option=com_staticxt&staticfile=show.php%3Ftitle=920&chapter=193200&layout=html&Itemid=27 as of 27 Aug 2012.
    - Current Ideas on Federalism, 1962 August 17 (Box 10)
      Bruno Leoni speaks about federalism in the United States.
    - Law, Economy, and Individual Freedom, 1962 August 20 (Box 10)
  - Felix Morley sound recordings
    - Freedom and Its Connection with Particular Forms of Government, 1959 June 15 (Box 7)
      Use copy available. Hoover Identifier 85023_a_0008243
      Morley delivers the introductory lecture to the Sixth Institute on Freedom and Competitive Enterprise, held at Claremont Men's College (later known as Claremont McKenna College) in Claremont, California.
    - A group discussion with Felix Morley, 1959 June 16 (Box 7)
      Use copy available. Hoover Identifier 85023_a_0008250
      "Free Society and Federalism"
    - Nature of Federal Form of Government, 1959 June 16 (Box 7)
      Use copy available. Hoover Identifier 85023_a_0008247_a01
      Morley examines federalism in the American system. In the process, he compares it to other forms of government in other countries, other eras, and Indian tribes. Occasionally through the lecture, he references the lecture of John Jewkes earlier that day. He places some importance on noting that the American system is not a political democracy.
    - Federal System (U.S.) of Divided and Septemberarated Power, 1959 June 17 (Box 7)
      Use copy available. Hoover Identifier 85023_a_0008251
      Morley lectures on the American federal system: of state governments, a national government, and the people's opinions thereon. One point he emphasizes is how misuse and abuse of words like national and federal have lead to a great deal of confusion in the country.
    - Response to Changing Characteristics of a Society in Political Government, 1959 June 18 (Box 7)
      Use copy available. Hoover Identifier 85023_a_0008254
      Morley looks at how government systems, with the focus on the American system, change shape over time, through amendment or Constitutional interpretation by the judiciary. In the process, he thoroughly analyzes the response to the 14th amendment and its ratification process.
    - Service State, 1959 June 19 (Box 7)
      Use copy available. Hoover Identifier 85023_a_0008257
      Morley looks at the political aspects of the welfare state and the permanence thereof.
    - Imperial Washington, 1959 June 22 (Box 7)
      Use copy available. Hoover Identifier 85023_a_0008259
      Morley lectures on how the United States' government is revealed in its international relations. He does this in showing how America is susceptible to the service state.
    - Tenacity of Tradition, 1959 June 24 (Box 7)
      Use copy available. Hoover Identifier 85023_a_0008260
      Morley lectures on the factors operating to maintain the system of federalism despite centralizing tendencies and pressures. Included is an analysis of the voting process and Electoral College.
    - Federalism, 1959 June 25 (Box 7)
      Use copy available. Hoover Identifier 85023_a_0008261
      Morley analyzes the importance of federalism as the nature of freedom.
    - United States Economy Has Vested Interest in Preparation for War, 1959 June 28 (Box 7)
      Use copy available. Hoover Identifier 85023_a_0008262
      Morley is troubled by the increasing reliance of the United States economy on defense spending since the end of World War II. Because of this, he looks at the foreign and military polices of the country. An important crux of his argument is the amount of democracy in a country's political system and its effectiveness.
    - The Theory of Government, 1962 August 14 (Box 10)
    - The Practice of Government, 1962 August 16 (Box 10)
  - Jacques Rueff sound recordings, 1955 June
    - The Monetary Mechanism and the Keynesian Theory, 1955 June 16 (Box 8)
      Use copy available. Hoover Identifier 85023_a_0008510
      Parable of the diner today
    - Monetary Theory and Economic Policy, 1955 June 17 (Box 8)
      Use copy available. Hoover Identifier 85023_a_0008511
    - Forty Years of Monetary Experience in Europe, 1955 June 18 (Box 8)
      Use copy available. Hoover Identifier 85023_a_0008512
      The very beginning of the talk is unavailable on the tape and thus on the digital file.
    - German Monetary Reform, 1955 June 20 (Box 8)
      Use copy available. Hoover Identifier 85023_a_0008517
    - Correlation of Unemployment to Wage and Price Mechanism, 1955 June 21 (Box 8)
      Use copy available. Hoover Identifier 85023_a_0008519
    - Jacques Rueff discussion seminar, 1955 June 21 (Box 8)
      Use copy available. Hoover Identifier 85023_a_0008518
    - European Community of Steel and Coal, 1955 June 22 (Box 8)
      Use copy available. Hoover Identifier 85023_a_0008524
    - View of a World Without Economic Intervention, 1955 June 24 (Box 8)
      Use copy available. Hoover Identifier 85023_a_0008525
      Rueff lectures on prices and the price system with liberal and socialist/communist economic systems.
    - How to Influence Those Who Don't Agree With Us, 1955 June 25 (Box 8)
      Use copy available. Hoover Identifier 85023_a_0008526
      A talk on the Marxist theory of surplus value
  - David McCord Wright sound recordings, 1955 June
    - Weakness of the Free World, 1955 June 13 (Box 8)
      Use copy available. Hoover Identifier 85023_a_0008529
      Wright speaks about the strengths and weaknesses the West and the communists possess in economic, social, moral, morale, and military matters.
      The sound quality is poor due to the tape's paper base.
    - David McCord Wright discussion seminar, 1955 June 20 (Box 8)
      Use copy available. Hoover Identifier 85023_a_0008530
      A discussion on Marxim, socialism, and capitalism.
    - German Economy vs. British Economy: A Comparison of the Post-War Rates of Recovery, 1955 June 21 (Box 8)
      Use copy available. Hoover Identifier 85023_a_0008533
      Wright examines why the German economy grew faster than the British economy following World War II, when both countries were devastated.
    - Barriers to Communication, 1955 June 22 (Box 8)
      Use copy available. Hoover Identifier 85023_a_0008534
      A talk about socialist and communist societies and how liberals can successfully engage, debate, and refute the socialist and communist ideas.
      As a follow up to Wright's claim in the lecture that universities ought to be able to show how many faculty members can provide the pro-capitalist/anti-communist arguments, Wright and Milton Friedman debate the makeup of university economic department faculties.
    - Wage Theory: Role of Unions in the Free Society, 1955 June 23 (Box 8)
      Use copy available. Hoover Identifier 85023_a_0008535
      Wright examines the effect of labor unions on wages, taking both a historical and a contemporary view. He believes union power is analogous to corporate power and that neither should be allowed to achieve too large a size.
    - David McCord Wright discussion seminar, 1955 June 24 (Box 9)
      Use copy available. Hoover Identifier 85023_a_0008536
    - Some Modern Confusions, 1955 June 24 (Box 9)
      Use copy available. Hoover Identifier 85023_a_0008537
      Wright speaks about capitalism, particularly the notion that capitalism and private property are the same thing. He goes on to compare and contrast the systems, such as, for one of many points, which system is most beneficial to artists.
  - Arthur Kemp sound recordings, 1962
    - Distribution of Wealth and Income, 1962 August 21 (Box 10)
    - The Welfare State: National Health Services, 1962 August 23 (Box 10)
      Arhur Kemp looks at the health care systems of the United States and the United Kingdom.
    - Economics of Social Security and Medical Care, 1962 August 24 (Box 10)
    - Foreign Aid and Assistance in a Free Society, 1962 August 28 (Box 10)
      A significant portion of Arthur Kemp's lecture is unavailable due to what sounds like a recording error at the time of initial creation.
    - Domestic Monetary Framework, 1962 June 29 (Box 9)
      Arhur Kemp speaks on the monetary policy of the United States, with both historical and contemporary considerations.
    - Economic Systems: Isms and Schisms, 1962 August 01 (Box 9)
      Arhur Kemp speaks about liberalism--as embodied in F. A. Hayek--in the contemporary world, especially as it relates to conservatism--as embodied by Russell Kirk--and what Americans refer to as liberalism, a kind focused on welfare.
    - The Role of Government and That of the Market and discussion, 1962 August 02 (Box 9)
      Arhur Kemp discusses the proper role of government and market forces in society, touching on broad topics such as paternalism before looking at how his ideas apply to specific issues. He speaks broadly, but often cites examples from and for the United States.
    - The Domestic Monetary Framework, 1962 August 03 (Box 9)
    - International Monetary Order, 1962 August 06 (Box 9)
    - Government's Role in Education and Similar Activities, 1962 August 07 (Box 9)
    - Common-Law Attitude Toward Monopoly, 1962 August 10 (Box 9)
  - Thomas LeDuc sound recordings, 1962 August
    - Environment and Human Intelligence, 1962 August 14 (Box 10)
    - Federalism and Anti-Federalism, 1962 August 01 (Box 9)
    - Historical Relativism and Objectivity, 1962 August 03 (Box 9)
    - Political Party Competition and Foreign Relations Before 1812, 1962 August 06 (Box 9)
      Thomas LeDuc speaks about the early foreign policy of the United States of America and how it intersects with economic and trade matters.
    - The Age of Jackson, 1962 August 07 (Box 9)
    - Fresh Thinking on the Reconstruction Period, 1962 August 08 (Box 9)
      Thomas LeDuc speaks about the United States following the Civil War including the legacy of Abraham Lincoln, the relationship between branches of government (President-Congress, House-Senate, etc.).
    - Eastern Migration as a Safety-Valve of Urban Discontent, 1962 August 09 (Box 9)
    - Turner's Frontier Hypothesis, 1962 August 10 (Box 9)
    - Agrarian Bias in American Historical Writing, 1962 August 13 (Box 9)
  - Sylvester Petro sound recordings, 1962 August
    - An Historical Survey of the Monopoly Problem, 1962 August 08 (Box 9)
    - Monopoly and Competition Identified, 1962 August 09 (Box 9)
    - Trade Unions and the Monopoly Problem, 1962 August 13 (Box 10)
  - Arthur A. Ekirch, Jr., sound recordings, 1962 August
    - Foundations of American Foreign Policy, 1962 August 15 (Box 10)
    - Manifest Destiny and the American Mission, 1962 August 16 (Box 10)
      Arthur Ekirch looks at American foreign policy through its history. He begins looking at the concept of Manifest Destiny. He uses this as a springboard to examine the American Revolution's influence throughout the world and America's later foreign relations throughout the world.
    - From Isolation to Imperialism, 1962 August 17 (Box 10)
      Arthur Ekirch looks at how the Progressive movement in the United States turned the country's foreign relations stance from isolationism to imperialism. Particular focus is placed on growing paternalism by the government in domestic affairs, President Roosevelt, Anglo-Saxon chauvinism/racism.
    - Changing U.S. Military Institutions, 1962 August 20 (Box 10)
    - Significance of the First World War, 1962 August 21 (Box 10)
      Arthur Ekirch argues that American involvement in World War I was the climax of the Progressive Era and caused the backlash against Progressivism. Key figures in his narrative are Wilson, Dewey, Bourne, and Carver. He further shows how war results in centralization of power.
    - Peace and Isolationism Between Wars, 1962 August 22 (Box 10)
      The bulk of this Arthur Ekirch talk is available, but is not a totally complete recording of the lecture.
    - The Coming of World War II, 1962 August 23 (Box 10)
    - Total War and Individual Freedom, 1962 August 24 (Box 10)
      Arthur Ekirch looks at the American experiences in war, particularly World War I and World War II, and the corresponding influence on economic freedom and civil liberties.
    - The Cold War in Perspective, 1962 August 27 (Box 10)
    - The Permanent War Economy and the Power Elite, 1962 August 28 (Box 10)
  - Louis M. Spadaro sound recordings, 1962 August
    - Liberal Economic Thought and Its Background, 1962 August 15 (Box 10)
      Louis M. Spadaro traces the history of Western and liberal economic thought from Plato, Aristotle, and the ancient Israelis through Adam Smith to the present.
    - The 19th Century Attack on Economic Liberalism, 1962 August 16 (Box 10)
    - The Neo-Classical Defense, 1962 August 17 (Box 10)
      Louis M. Spadaro focuses on defending against the ideas of Marx.
    - The Basic Issues: An Evaluation, 1962 August 21 (Box 10)
  - Miscellaneous sound recordings
    - James Doenges talk at the Freedom School on Social Security, 1957 August 04 (Box 1)
      Use copy available. Hoover Identifier 85023_a_0005892
    - Pepperdine lecture by Dr. William Mayer, 1961 April 19 (Box 1)
      Use copy available. Hoover Identifier 85023_a_0008755
      This lecture concerns communist management of American soldiers in captivity in Korea.
    - Is Collective Defense Possible?, 1961 July 24 (Box 1)
      Use copy available. Hoover Identifier 85023_a_0005893
      James Doenges speaks at the Freedom School.
    - An Individual's Defense, 1961 July 30 (Box 1)
      Use copy available. Hoover Identifier 85023_a_0008752
      LeFevre speaks on the individual's rights to defend themselves and their property.
      The sound quality on the accessioned tape is poor.
    - Sandia lecture by Dr. William Mayer, 1955-1977 (Box 1)
      Use copy available. Hoover Identifier 85023_a_0008756
      Dr. Mayer speaks about a study of U.S. prisoners of war in Korea. He says the Koreans have developed, as much as possible, the ultimate weapon: brainwashing prisoners of war.
    - H. W. Luhnow remarks about the Mayer film 'What Can I Do?', 1961 December (Box 1)
      Speaking to the employees of the Volker Company, Luhnow comments on what Americans can do to re-instill the American spirit in themselves and resist communism. He calls for increased Christianity in America as part of this.
    - What Can I Do?, 1968 August 02 (Box 1)
      James M. Rogers speech
    - Proofs of a Conspiracy, 1969 November 01 (Box 1)
      "Proofs of a Conspiracy" - A Seminar conducted by Stuart R. Crane, Ph.D.
      Bob Jones, of the university of the same name, introduces Crane.
      The program from the event lists the subjects of the talk as:
      - Why the super-rich support socialism.
      - The interlock between the super-rich and the left.
      - How history is distorted by the educators and the news media.
      - Why big business wants government controls.
      - How the U.S. finances Communism.
      - The Establishment's control of Communism.
      - Why the federal government wants riots.
      - Why the Black Nationalists and the New Left are really tools of the Establishment.
      - Why Nixon continues LBJ's policies.
      - Why the Establishment must have no-win wars.
      While this inventory matches the content of the talk, other paper materials included with the tape indicate the talk happened in Massachusetts. However, during the recording, Crane indicates that the event takes place in California.
    - Interview with Professor W. H. Hutt, 1971 July 14 (Box 1)
      Description on the back of the tape box reads:
      Interview with Prof. W. H. Hutt by W. M. Evers III, H. G. Resch, Mark Venezia, Jonathan Kahn, and John Hagel on the evening of 13 July '71.
    - Road to Serfdom + 30 Years, 1973 January 20 (Box 1)
      Arthur Shenfield examines the ideas in F. A. Hayek's book The Road to Serfdom and how they apply to the world since publication of the book. He believes the world has not turned away from the road to serfdom directly, however, the book has indirectly influenced economic policy.
    - Resources, Wealth, and Economic Growth, 1962 August 08 (Box 9)
      Scott Gordon lecture
    - Conservation and Utilization of Natural Resources, 1962 August 09 (Box 9)
      Scott Gordon looks at natural resources from the economist's perspective. Topics include, but are not limited to, ephemeral resources; the economist's prefered usage level of renewable resources than those of, for example, fisherman; resource conservation as investment; resources as market competitors; food and farming economics.
    - Interview with Ludwig Lachmann, 1974 July 17 (Box 10)
      This interview concerns the history of economic thought, Austrian school, South African conditions, etc.
    - Methods of Sociology, 1962 August 22 (Box 10)
      The bulk of this James w. Wiggins talk is available, but is not a totally complete recording of the lecture.
- Offce Files, 1970-1975
  Scope and Contents
  Materials comprised of various administrative records including: correspondence, contracts, memoranda, and financial documents.
  - Correspondence with Bettina Bien (samples of Mises signatures), 1971 (Box-folder 11: 1)
  - Dot Design cost estimates - Mises 90th, contract with Edwards, 1970-1972 (Box-folder 11: 2)
  - Hayek, 1975 fellowship (Box-folder 11: 3)
  - Mises Festschrift, Curran Library (Toward Liberty), 1971-1972 (Box-folder 11: 4)
  - Mises 90th Festschrift planning, 1971 (Box-folder 11: 5)
  - Mises, Ludwig von, 1972-1973 (Box-folder 11: 6)
  - Mises 90th Solicitations, financial contributions, 1970-1971 (Box-folder 11: 7)
  - Towards Liberty reprints, 1970-1972 (Box-folder 11: 8)